A Finding Aid to the Agnes Pelton Papers, 1885-1989, in the Archives of American Art AAA.peltagne
Archives of American Art
Agnes Pelton papers
1885-1989
AAA.peltagne
Archives of American Art
1.8 Linear feet
The papers of painter Agnes Pelton measure 1.8 linear feet and date from 1885-1989. Found within the papers are biographical materials; business and personal correspondence, many addressed to Jane Levington Comfort; writings; printed material; 3 mixed media scrapbooks; artwork, including loose sketches and 9 sketchbooks; and photographs of Pelton, her family and friends, and her work.
Pelton, Agnes, 1881-1961
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Agnes Pelton papers were assembled by Cornelia and Irving Sussman for a biography of Agnes Pelton. They were donated to the Archives by gallery director Jan Rindfleisch on behalf of the Sussmans, in 1984. In 1997, circa 162 letters from Agnes Pelton to Jane Levington Comfort, that are now part of this collection, were bequeathed to Cornelia and Irving Sussman by Jane Levington Comfort through Joan Crisci, the executor of Comfort’s estate, and donated to the Archives.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of this collection are available on 35 mm legacy microfilm reels 3426-3427 at the Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. The 162 letters from Agnes Pelton to Jane Levington Comfort have not been microfilmed. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archvies' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Biographical/Historical note
Painter Agnes Pelton (1881-1961) lived and worked in Long Island, New York and Cathedral City, California and is known for her desert landscapes, portraits, and abstract paintings.
Born in Stuttgart, Germany to William and Florence Pelton, Pelton and her mother relocated to New York after her father's death in 1890. Her mother, who had studied music at the Stuttgart Conservatory, opened the Pelton School of Music in Brooklyn, which remained in operation for 30 years. Pelton began her art studies at the Pratt Institute in 1895 and continued working with one of her instructors, Arthur Dow, at his summer school in Ipswich, Massachusetts after her graduation in 1900. She later worked with William Langson Lathrop and Hamilton Field, and traveled abroad to attend the British Academy in Rome in 1910 and 1911.
In 1912, after seeing her work in an exhibition in Hamilton Field's studio in Ogunquit, Maine, Walt Kuhn invited Pelton to participate in the 1913 Armory Show. During her early career, Pelton created works that were primarily influenced by Davies's philosophy on the effect of natural light, and which she termed "Imaginative Paintings." After a visit to New Mexico in 1919, Pelton began shifting to another style of painting, focusing on Southwestern landscapes and figurative portraits, which she continued from her studios in New York City and Long Island. In 1932, Pelton moved to Cathedral City, California and began painting abstract works in a new stylistic phase, which were visual explorations of her growing interest in spirituality and philosophy. In 1938, she became a founding member of the Transcendental Painting Group, which included Raymond Jonson and Emil Bisttram. Pelton died in Cathedral City in 1961.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter Agnes Pelton measure 1.8 linear feet and date from 1885-1989. Found within the papers are biographical materials; business and personal correspondence, many addressed to Jane Levington Comfort; writings; printed material; 3 mixed media scrapbooks; artwork, including loose sketches and 9 sketchbooks; and photographs of Pelton, her family and friends, and her work.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1898-1989 (2 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1930-1980 (0.4 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, 1913-1956 (8 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1913-1955 (6 folders; Box 1)
Series 5: Scrapbooks, 1911-1950 (0.4 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 6: Artwork, 1885-1957 (0.5 linear feet; Boxes 2-3)
Series 7: Photographic Material, 1886-1955 (0.4 linear feet; Box 3)
Annixter, Jane; Painters--California; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Women artists--California
- Biographical Materials, 1898-1989; Series 1; 2 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials consist of curriculum vitae and letters, notes, and printed material from Florence Pelton, Agnes's mother.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1930-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Florence Pelton Papers (mother), circa 1898-1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1930-1980; Series 2; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence includes letters to business colleagues and friends, including Raymond Jonson, Dane Rudhyar, and Jane Levington Comfort. Letters to Jonson and Rudhyar relate to their affiliation and work as officers of the Transcendental Painting Group. 162 letters to Comfort date from 1930 to 1960 and include descriptions of Pelton's work, upcoming exhibitions, travels, life in the desert, and relationships with friends and family. There are also partial typed transcriptions of the Comfort letters completed by Pelton's biographer Cornelia Sussman.
  Materials are arranged chronologically by recipient.
  - Comfort, Jane Levington, circa 1930-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Comfort, Jane Levington, 1930-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4-12)
  - Transcriptions of Letters to Jane Comfort, by Cornelia Sussman, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters to Others, circa 1938-1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Writings, 1913-1956; Series 3; 8 Folders Box 1
  Writings include price lists for works of art, poetry, a notebook annotating exhibitions and other events dating from 1913 to 1915, and organizational information on the Transcendental Painting Group.
  - Lists of Artwork, circa 1934-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Notebook, Activities and Exhibitions, 1913-1915 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Items Inserted in Notebook, 1913-1915 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - On Abstract Painting, circa 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Poetic Introductions", 1934 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Poetic Introductions" (drafts), circa 1934 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Transcendental Painting Group, circa 1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1935-1950 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Printed Material, 1913-1955; Series 4; 6 Folders Box 1
  Printed material consists of clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and reproductions of artwork.
  - Clippings, circa 1924-1951 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, circa 1913-1955 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, circa 1924-1951 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1935-1950 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Scrapbooks, 1911-1950; Series 5; 0.4 Folders Box 1
  The three mixed media scrapbooks include newspaper and magazine clippings, exhibition programs, correspondence, original photographs, and other miscellany relating to Pelton and her career.
  Materials are arranged in chronological order.
  - Scrapbook I, 1911-1931 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Items Removed from Scrapbook I, 1911-1931 (Box 1, Folder 30-33)
  - Scrapbook II, 1931-1950 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Items Removed from Scrapbook II, 1931-1950 (Box 1, Folder 35-36)
  - Scrapbook III, circa 1924-1939 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Artwork, 1885-1957; Series 6; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  Artwork consists of loose sketches of figures and abstract forms. The 9 sketchbooks are of childhood drawings, landscapes, figures, and flowers. Annotated notebook/sketchbooks include notes, thoughts, and dated entries with some accompanying illustrations and sketches.
  Materials are arranged chronologically by document type.
  - Loose Sketches, circa 1935-1950 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Sketchbook I, Childhood Drawings, 1885-1886 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook II, 1911-1922 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook III, circa 1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notebook/Sketchbook IV, circa 1917-1929 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Notebook/Sketchbook V, 1929-1931 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Notebook/Sketchbook VI, 1930-1935 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Notebook/Sketchbook VII, circa 1931 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Notebook/Sketchbook VIII, circa 1936-1943 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Notebook/Sketchbook IX, 1942-1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Photographic Material, 1886-1955; Series 7; 0.4 Linear feet Box 3
  Photographs are of Pelton, her family and friends, and her work. They include images taken from her home and studio, as well as artist models and photos from her travels.
  Materials are arranged by subject and document type.
  - Agnes Pelton and Family, circa 1890-1950 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Family and Friends, circa 1886-1940 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Artist Models, circa 1920-1930 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Farmhouse, Windmill, Travel Scenes, circa 1935-1950 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1920-1950 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Works of Art, Abstracts, circa 1940-1955 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Works of Art, Figurative, circa 1940-1955 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Works of Art, Landscapes, circa 1940-1955 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Works of Art, Portraits, circa 1940-1955 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Works of Art, On Display, circa 1940-1955 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Works of Art, Negatives, circa 1940-1955 (Box 3, Folder 13)